Guide to the Alumni Class materials, 1823-1998 MS2130
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Personal papers, 1823-1993; MS2130 Series 4; 4 Linear feet (Box 27, Box 30, Box 12, Box 32, Box 3, Box 39, Flat box 24, Box 34, Box 15)
  - The Lyric Poetry of Tennyson and other notes, 1920 ca. (Box 27, Folder 15)
    A native of Florida, James Lewis Lofton Moneyway received his A.B. in 1912 and his A.M in 1922 from George Washington University. While a student at GW, Moneyway was actively involved in the Chemical Society and in the Calcium Club, a dramatic society. He was class editor of the Department of Arts and Sciences between 1910 and 1912. In his professional career, Moneyway worked for the U.S. Postal Service and was the Director of Moneyway Studios. This collection was originally in the form of a scrapbook, and its provenance is unknown. The newspaper clippings were copied unto acid-free paper and the originals disposed of. Materials include "The Lyric Poetry of Tennyson" prepared by Moneyway and other notes and poetry. They date from ca.1920. Formerly ACC#869.
  - Dance cards, report card, 1912 -1923 (Box 27, Folder 16)
    A native of Florida, James Lewis Lofton Moneyway received his A.B. in 1912 and his A.M in 1922 from George Washington University. While a student at GW, Moneyway was actively involved in the Chemical Society and in the Calcium Club, a dramatic society. He was class editor of the Department of Arts and Sciences between 1910 and 1912. In his professional career, Moneyway worked for the U.S. Postal Service and was the Director of Moneyway Studios. This collection was originally in the form of a scrapbook, and its provenance is unknown. The newspaper clippings were copied unto acid-free paper and the originals disposed of. Materials include programs to dances (1912-13), Moneyway's report card (June 5, 1912), and Alumni Quarterly newsletter (March 23, 1923). They date from 1912-23. Formerly ACC#869.
  - Programs, sketches, news clippings, 1912 -1923 (Box 27, Folder 17)
    A native of Florida, James Lewis Lofton Moneyway received his A.B. in 1912 and his A.M in 1922 from George Washington University. While a student at GW, Moneyway was actively involved in the Chemical Society and in the Calcium Club, a dramatic society. He was class editor of the Department of Arts and Sciences between 1910 and 1912. In his professional career, Moneyway worked for the U.S. Postal Service and was the Director of Moneyway Studios. This collection was originally in the form of a scrapbook, and its provenance is unknown. The newspaper clippings were copied unto acid-free paper and the originals disposed of. Materials include programs to theatrical productions, sketches (including one of Moneyway), and news clippings on drama and novelist Augusta Evans Wilson. They date from ca.1910. Formerly ACC#869.
  - Back to the U.S.S.R, 1976 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    Paper entitled "Back to the U.S.S.R" (1976) by Sondra Claudine Langtry (M.A. 1974). Sondra Claudine Langtry (1944-1982) spent four months traveling in the Soviet Union in 1976. She spent time in Odessa and Kiev relaying information about what she encountered in terms of living conditions and people she interacted with both in the government and on the street. Langtry's journal of this time "Back to the USSR" recounts her many experiences during this time in her life. During her trip she assisted her father in locating some of the relatives he had not spoken to since his departure from Russia in 1920. Langtry received her M.A. in Russian Literature from The George Washington University in 1974. She also received degrees from the University of Texas at Austin and American University. She died in 1982.
    Formely ACC#741.
  - Compositions by Lena Nelson, 1884 -1916 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    A native of Washington DC, Robert Nelson Anderson spent his academic, professional and social life in the area. He was a 1917 high school graduate of the McKinley Manual Training School. At the Columbian College of George Washington University, R. Anderson was president of the 1921 graduating class. He was also an active member of the Delta Tau Delta fraternity and the Phi Alpha Delta legal fraternity. Upon being conferred his Bachelor of Arts degree in 1921, R. Anderson went on to earn a Bachelor of Law in 1923. Soon there after he was appointed as Special Assistant to the Attorney General of the United States. In his latter life he was a member of the Sons of Confederate Veterans and president of the Arlington County Civic Federation. He had at least one son, William Gerald, with his wife, Mary Elizabeth.
    This folder contains: Compositions by Lena Nelson (possible mother of R. Anderson); notification of award to R. Anderson, Sept. 7, 1916; Philosophy exam, May 19, 1884; "A Woman's Question";. "Early Impressions" by Daysie Timberlake; "Archie Dean"; History Question, Feb. 3, 1885; Letter to mother, Oct. 14, 1884; "Chris Columbus" Feb. 16, 1884; "Why are you not a Christian?"
    Formerly ACC#419
  - Incoming Correspondence: scheduling of football games, 1916 (Box 32, Folder 2)
    This folder contains: Incoming Correspondences re: scheduling of football games, 1916
  - GWU mementos, 1918 -1923 (Box 32, Folder 3)
    This folder contains: GWU mementos from: student council, correspondence, report cards (1918- 20), class president elections, Junior Prom invitations, commencement program (1923), commencement announcement and activities (1921); debate announcement, GW "letter" certificate.
  - McKinley Manual Training School mementos, 1913 -1917 (Box 32, Folder 4)
    This folder contains: McKinley Manual Training School mementos: commencement invitation and program (1913); report cards (1914-1917); prohibition postcard contest entry; various from Junior Epworth League of St. Paul Church; Young Christian Men's Association membership card; essays entitled "The Influence of the Assumption of Innocence", April 23, 1917, and "The Thing of Exposition "A Sonnet" Nov. 22, 1916; Matthew G. Emery School: 1st-8th grade report cards (no 4th grade).
  - Manuscript by Mrs. Mary Stuart Carden, "Status of Education in Virginia" from 1760-1770, 1942 ca. (Box 32, Folder 5)
    This folder contains: Manuscript by Mrs. Mary Stuart Carden, "Status of Education in Virginia" from 1760-1770, ca.1942
  - Daughters of the American Revolution, 1943 (Box 32, Folder 6)
    This folder contains: Daughters of the American Revolution 1943 speech and correspondence regarding "Life and Activities of Abraham Baldwin"; correspondence regarding "I am an American Day", 1943
  - Club Memberships, Academic Institution Memberships, 1928 -1959 (Box 32, Folder 7)
    This folder contains: Club Memberships, Academic Institution Memberships and other honors: Virginia Historical Society, July 10, 1939; Administration Law Section of DC Bar Association, Oct. 16, 1946; Washington Golf and Country Club, 1934, 1938; Social Register of Virginia, 1936; American Judicature Society, 1948; City Club, Feb. 11, 1928; American Academy of Political Science; Library of Congress Portrait of R. Anderson, 1956; American Society of International Law, Dec. 29, 1959, July 16, 1952; National All Faith Memorial, July 18, 1949.
  - Arlington County, Virginia Citizen Association correspondence, 1933 -1966 (Box 32, Folder 8)
    This folder contains: Arlington County, Virginia Citizen Association correspondence, 1933-66
  - Sons of Confederate Veterans (UCV) correspondence and mementos, 1919 -1940 (Box 32, Folder 9)
    This folder contains: Sons of Confederate Veterans (UCV) correspondence and mementos, 1919-1940: programs, membership cards, blank stationary with letterhead, By-laws of UCV, list of 1932 officers.
  - Newspaper clippings about Judge John B. Payne, 1922 -1938 (Box 32, Folder 10)
    This folder contains: Newspaper clippings about Judge John B. Payne: career and American Red Cross service (originals and photocopies), 1922-38
  - Fraternity mementos from Delta Tau Delta and Phi Alpha Delta, 1926 -1956 (Box 32, Folder 11)
    This folder contains: Fraternity mementos from Delta Tau Delta and Phi Alpha Delta: rosters, invitations, newsletters, 1926-56
  - Booklet and poem, 1929 (Box 32, Folder 12)
    This folder contains: book titled "Woman's Missionary Society", 1929 ('Mrs. Anderson" written on front page and loose notes inside); poem "The Rarest Pearl" by S.F. Fiesten, inscribed by author.
  - Newspaper clippings about Robert Anderson, 1919 -1922 (Box 32, Folder 13)
    This folder contains: Newspaper clippings about Robert Anderson, mostly from GWU Hatchet (originals and photocopies), 1919-22
  - University Hatchet issues, 1920 -1922 (Box 32, Folder 14)
    This folder contains: The University Hatchet: issues from Feb. 26, 1920; March 11, 1920; Oct. 21, 1921; Nov. 4, Feb. 3, 10, 14, 17, 1922; March 10 & 17, 1922; April 28, 1922; May 5, 1922.
  - Desegregation in the District of Columbia, 1956 -1958 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    Contains two articles by Paul Cooke in the "Journal of Negro Education," 1956 and 1958 that detail desegregation in all D.C. colleges and universities.
    Andrew J. Novak (1983- ) was a student at George Washington University when he donated this collection to the library in 2004. He was the Historical Research editor for the student newspaper "The Hatchet" for the 2003-04 academic year, and majored in International Relations at the Elliott School of International Relations. He also worked as a student assistant in the University Archives in 2004-05. Mr. Novak's interest in the history of the university in general, and former president Cloyd Heck Marvin (1927-59) in particular, led him to research and write a book titled "The Man in the Gray Flannel Suit: A Critical Portrait of Cloyd Heck Marvin. " The book was self-published by WORDPRO Press in Ithaca, New York in 2004.
    Marvin's term in office was marred by almost constant friction with liberal elements of the student body and alumni, and his disputes with the faculty boiled over into protest several times and nearly led to an investigation by the American Association of University Professors (AAUP). The AAUP never investigated his term at George Washington, though they were appealed to do so many times; they did conduct an investigation of his administration at Arizona, however, and were quite critical of Marvin's lack of respect for faculty tenure and academic freedom.
    Formerly ACC#1053
  - Discrimination against Jewish students, 1950 (Box 34, Folder 2)
    Contains Hatchet article on 1950 incident with Jewish students. See also articles in "The Evening Star" (Feb. 22, 1950), and "The Washington Post" (Feb. 23, 1950). The Hillel collection (former Acc #509), contains further information on this topic.
  - Faculty Appeal: Lester K. Born, 1936 (Box 34, Folder 3)
    Contains Dr. Lester K. Born's (Dept. of Classical Languages) appeal to the AAUP following his dismissal, including an explanation of events and correspondence with Dr. Marvin, 1936.
  - Faculty Appeal: Constance Connor Brown, 1937 (Box 34, Folder 4)
    Contains Constance Connor Brown's (Dept. of Public Speaking) appeal to the AAUP following her forced resignation. Also contains a copy of a flyer from Brown's theater company, 1937.
  - Faculty Appeal: Georgette Caskie, 1947 -1959 (Box 34, Folder 5)
    Contains a handwritten copy of Georgette Caskie's (Dept. of Romance Languages) appeal to the AAUP, 1946. The original is contained in the AAUP records. Also contains a newspaper clipping from 1959, courtesy Southwest Missouri State University.
  - Faculty Appeal: James Defandorf, 1938 (Box 34, Folder 6)
    Contains a copy of James Defandorf's (Dept. of Pharmacology) appeal to the AAUP following Marvin's refusal to promote him, 1938. The appeal also contains correspondence with Marvin and a list of Defandorf's publications.
  - Faculty Appeal: John Elson, 1936 (Box 34, Folder 7)
    Contains a copy of Dr. John Elson's (Dept. of English) appeal to the AAUP following Marvin's refusal to reappoint him, 1936.
  - Faculty Appeal: Martha Gibbon, 1940 (Box 34, Folder 8)
    Contains a copy of Martha Gibbon's (Dept. of English) appeal to the AAUP following her resignation in 1940; various correspondences with Ralph Himstead, general-secretary of the AAUP; student petitions and flyers; copies of pictures of Miss Gibbon; newspaper articles; other miscellaneous sources.
  - Faculty Appeal: Marvin T. Herrick, 1937 (Box 34, Folder 9)
    Contains a copy of Marvin T. Herrick's (Dept. of English) appeal to the AAUP in 1937; some correspondence with President Marvin and with General-Secretary Ralph Himstead; a copy of the student petition on behalf of Dr. Herrick.
  - Faculty Appeal: Evelyn Jones Kirmse, 1984 (Box 34, Folder 10)
    Contains a copy of recollections of Marvin made by Evelyn Jones Kirmse in 1984. She was assistant dean of women at GW until 1929 before she left for the University of Arizona, and provides insights on both Marvin's term in Tucson and in Washington.
  - Faculty Appeal: Elizabeth Lathrop, 1936 (Box 34, Folder 11)
    Contains a copy of Elizabeth Lathrop's (Division of Library Science) appeal to the AAUP in 1936. [Also see Elmer Louis Kayser's oral interview on Alfred Schmidt, University Librarian and head of Division of Library Science in former ACC#239.]
  - Faculty Appeal: Medical School reorganization, 1932 (Box 34, Folder 12)
    Contains a copy of faculty petition to AAUP signed by fired professors; list of complaints against Dr. Marvin; memorandum concerning Medical School reorganization; and complete list of professors fired, 1932.
  - Faculty Appeal: Truman Michelson, 1932 (Box 34, Folder 13)
    Contains copies of internal memoranda of AAUP officers; copy of Mr. Truman Michelson's (Dept. of Anthropology) appeal to the AAUP in 1932; various biographies and notes on Mr. Michelson; article on Anthropology courses from 1919; contact information for Truman Michelson Papers at National Anthropological Archives.
  - Faculty Appeal: Alva Curtis Wilgus, 1936 (Box 34, Folder 14)
    Contains copy of Alva Curtis Wilgus's (Dept. of History ) appeal to the AAUP in 1936. See also "Hatchet" article May 19, 1936.
  - University of Arizona - AAUP investigation, 1924 -1927 (Box 34, Folder 16)
    Contains press releases, reports, and correspondence pertaining to the AAUP investigation of the Cloyd Heck Marvin administration at the University of Arizona in 1924-27.
  - Student and Alumni Investigations of Faculty Dismissals, 1937 -1940 (Box 34, Folder 15)
    Contains reports of investigations of Marvin's violations of faculty tenure and academic freedom by students (1937) and alumni (1940), following the Herrick and Gibbon cases, respectively.
  - University of Arizona - Board of Regents and Governor, 1923 (Box 34, Folder 17)
    Contains correspondence and biographical information of the University of Arizona Board of Regents during the Marvin administration and of Governor George W.P. Hunt, indicating the politics of the Board, 1923.
  - University of Arizona - Freemasons - School of Government at GWU, 1928 (Box 34, Folder 18)
    Contains correspondence among a prominent University of Arizona administrator, Gordon Butler, Dean of School of Mines; a prominent Arizona freemason, Harry Drachman; and John Henry Cowles, Scottish Rite commander in Washington concerning the establishment of School of Government at GW and Marvin's role, 1928.
  - University of Arizona - Impeachment and Resignation, 03/1926 --01/1927 (Box 34, Folder 19)
    Contains information relating to Cloyd Heck Marvin's impeachment trials and resignation from the presidency of the University of Arizona, Mar. 1926 - Jan. 1927. Contains correspondence, newspaper articles, and complete transcript of the impeachment trials.
  - University of Arizona - Presidency of Cloyd Heck Marvin, 1922 -1927 (Box 34, Folder 20)
    Contains brief overviews of the Marvin administration at the University of Arizona, by Mary Huntington Abbott and Douglas Martin, 1922-27.
  - The Man in the Gray Flannel Suit: A Critical Portrait of Dr. Cloyd Heck Marvin, 2004 (Box 34, Folder 21)
    Contains a copy of Andrew Novak's book on Marvin, 2004. Copyright law governs commercial use of the book.
  - United States and Brazilian Naval Relations, 1939-1945, 1971 (Box 39, Folder 1)
    Naval War College thesis (submitted to GW School of Public and International Affairs) by Barr Stevenson. Formerly ACC#629.
  - Two envelopes addressed to Anna S. Hazelton, 1881; Series 4 (Box 39, Folder 2)
    This folder containes two envelopes ("postal documents") addressed to Anna S. Hazelton, member of the Columbian College class of 1892. One envelope is addressed to her in Washington D.C. and one in New York.
  - Graduation Materials from Charles H. Cragin, Jr., 29 June 1870 (Box 39, Folder 3)
    This folder consists of an annotated commencement program, commencement invitation and typescript of a graduating speech titled "The Microcosm", all belonging to Charles H. Cragin, Jr., Columbia College class of 1870.
- Diplomas, certificates, awards, 1826-1995; MS2130 Series 5; 3 Linear feet (Flat box 13, Flat box 37, Box 35, Flat box 38, Folder 1, Box 10, Box 4, Box 5, Box 11, Flat box 28, Box 31)
  This collections consists of diplomas, ceritificates, awards, and citations belonging to various alumni. The dates range from 1826 to 1995.
  - Deborah Seigel Parker diplomia, 09/30/1971 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    A diploma of Deborah Seigal Parker, which dates from 1971. The diploma is in its holder and original box. Parker graduated from The George Washington University in with an M.A. in Guidance from the Graduate School of Education and Human Development.
    The material was donated to the University Archives by Janice F. Goldblum, Parker's cousin, in 1994. Formerly ACC# 322.
  - Julius Axelrod awards and law school diploma, undated; Series 5 (Flat box 38, Folder 1)
  - Arthur Millard Trivett, diploma, 05/30/1904 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    This diploma is for Artur Millard Trivett achievement of Doctor of Dental Surgery from the Dental School of the Columbian University.
    They range in date from 1825-1904 and were transferred to University Archives by the Dimock Gallery in 2000.
    Formerly ACC# 870.
  - Resolution of National Geographic Society to Esther Manion, 03/30/1973 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    National Geographic Society Resolution to Esther Manion (GW A.B. 1928; M.A. 1932) for 50 Years of service, signed By Gilbert Grosvenor, Mar. 30, 1973 (See also GW Magazine, Vol.2:3, Fall 1965, p.28]. Donation from Hilda Jay in 2001. Esther Ann Manion (1900-92) was the Head Librarian of the National Geographic Society in Washington, D.C. from 1946-65. Esther Manion was born September 29, 1900 in Buffalo, New York. She received her early scholastic training at Holy Angels School in Buffalo, Mount St. Joseph in Attica, New York, and Sacred Heart Convent in Washington, D.C. Manion earned an A.B. with distinction (Library Science) in 1928 and A.M. in geography in 1932 from The George Washington University.
    Before joining the National Geographic staff in 1922, she was employed by the District of Columbia Board of Education. Ms. Manion was made librarian in 1929, and head in 1946, where she remained until her retirement in 1965. During her time there, the library grew from about 3,000 volumes to 43,000. She continued to work for the Society after retiring as Librarian, and was hon0red in 1973 for fifty years of service.
    Ms. Manion was a founding member of the District chapter of the Special Libraries Association. She was a member of the Association of American Geographers, Daughters of the American Revolution, and the General Society of Mayflower Descendants. Ms. Manion died January 12, 1992.
    N.B. This history note was written in 2005
    Formerly Acc#998.
  - Diplomas of Woodbury Wheeler and John Hill Wheeler, 1826 -1866 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Diplomas of Woodbury Wheeler (A.B. 1866; LL.B. 1867; A.M. 1869) from 1866 and 1867. Also contains diplomas of his father, John Hill Wheeler (A.B. 1826; M.A. 1835) along with his father's certificate of membership in the Enosinian Society and another award. All documents are in Latin. Formerly ACC#1020.
  - Diploma of Anne D. Cordero, 02/22/1968 (Flat box 13, Folder 1)
    Diploma of Anne Deing Cordero, the degree of Doctor of Philosophy, awarded February 22, 1968. Her field of study was French Language and Literature, and her dissertation was titled "Symbols of Tension in the Theater of the Absurd." She received a Diplom Dolmetscher from Johannes-Gutenberg Universitat, Germany in 1955 and an M.A. from University of Florida in 1957. Formerly ACC#558.
  - Diplomas of George C. Samson, 1865 -1868 (Flat box 13, Folder 2)
    Diplomas of George C. Samson; A.B. 1865 and A.M. 1868. Samson was the son of Columbian College President George W. Samson, and he earned and A.B. in 1865, an M.D. in 1867, and an A.M. in 1868 from the college. He was later in charge of the Soldiers' and Sailors' Orphan Home, Washington, D.C., 1870-79; served on the Board of Trustees for the Public Schools of the District of Columbia, 1878-82; served as a Board Manager for the YMCA, Washington D.C., 1891-97; served as a Board Manager for the Washington City Bible Society, 1888-99; served as Treasurer of the Baptist Social Union, District of Columbia, 1898-99; and was a member of the Medical Society of the District of Columbia. Formerly ACC#964.
  - Diploma of George Nordlinger as Doctor of Medicine, 06/07/1922 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Certificate from A.F.A. King Obstetrical Society of GWU, 05/1941 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    George Nordlinger (1897-1994) was a member of The George Washington University community for over three quarters of a century, as a student, faculty member and emeritus professor. Formerly ACC#1052.
  - Certificate from GWU General Alumni Association, for 25 years of service as a teacher, 10/28/1950 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Citation from President Thomas H. Carroll conferring Emeritus status as Professor of Clinical Obstetrics and Gynecology, 06/06/1962 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Citation from Jacobi Society of Washington to Nordlinger as President, undated (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Certificate from American Board of Obstetrics and Gynecology, 05/1948 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Certificate from Washington Gynecological Society, for services as President, 1949-50, 1958 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Certificate from Fifty Year Club of medical practice, 1972 ca. (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - A.H. Robbins Community Service Award, Medical Society of D.C., 11/16/1988 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Certificate from Grand Lodge of Free and Accepted Masons for 75 years of service, 1995 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Plaque - Jewish Social Service Agency letter of appreciation to Isaac Nordlinger (GW LL.B. 1933), 05/25/1976 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - William P. Ellenberger Diplomas, 1897 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    This folder contains two of William P. Ellenberger's Diplomas for the Doctor of Veterinarian Medicine degree, 1897.
    William P. Ellenberger was born about 1870 or 1871 in Knoxville, Tenn. He received his Doctorate in Veterinarian Medicine from the Columbian University, now GW University, in 1897. This note was written in 2005. Formerly Acc 522.
  - Diplomas of George W. Selzer, 1918 -1919 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    Two George Washington University diplomas from George W. Salzer. One is a B.A. degree from 1918 and the other is a M.S. degree from 1919. These diplomas are made of sheepskin. Also included is correspondence from Jane Hansen, daughter of George W. Salzer and President Stephen Joel Trachtenberg and a brief biography on George W. Salzer. Formerly Acc#480.
  - Pyramid Award, Pyramid Pin, GWU medallion, and Letterman certificate, 1925 ca. (Box 31, Folder 8)